{"tossups": [{"question": "A revolt of this force burned the Scutari Barracks due to reforms known as Nizam-I Cedid [[NEE-zahm-EE seh-DEED]], or the \"New Order.\" In a modernization effort, this force was disbanded following the Auspicious Incident by Mahmud II. The<em> devshirme</em> system originally recruited young, Christian boys into this military corps, which was tasked with protecting the sultan in battle. For the point, name this elite, musket-wielding corps of Ottoman infantry.", "answer": "<b><u>Janissaries</u></b> (or <b><u>Janissary</u></b> Corps; accept <b><u>Ye</u><u>\u014b</u><u>i\u00e7eri</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This man used the cousin of Amerigo Vespucci [[veh-SPOO-chee]], Simonetta, as the model for the title nymph in<em> The Death of Procris</em>. Cosimo, Piero, and a young Lorenzo D' Medici all appear in this man's artwork<em> Adoration of the Magi</em>. This man became a fervent member of the \"Weepers,\" followers of Friar Savonarola [[sah-voh-nah-ROH-lah]], and willingly destroyed several of his own works of art. For the point, name this artist of<em> The</em> <em>Birth of Venus</em> and<em> Primavera</em>.", "answer": "Sandro <b><u>Botticelli</u></b> (or Alessandro di Mariano di Vanni <b><u>Filipepi</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This man likely gave the sharpshooter Annie Oakley her nickname \"Little Sure Shot.\" Alfred Sully's deployment of artillery led to his victory over this general during the Battle of the Badlands, a part of the larger Dakota Wars. With Crazy Horse, this man eradicated the 7th Cavalry of George Custer at the Battle of Little Bighorn. The Ghost Dance movement was supported by, for the point, which Hunkpapa Lakota chief?", "answer": "<b><u>Sitting Bull</u></b> (or <b><u>T</u><u>\u021f</u><u>at</u><u>\u021f</u><u>\u00e1</u><u>\u014b</u><u>ka \u00cdyotake</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In a Kalidasa play in this language, the celestial nypmh Urvasi is turned into a vine. The likely-fictional Kaurava and Pandava families battle in the dynastic Kurukshetra [[koo-rook-SHEH-trah]] War in an epic poem in this tongue. A subset of this language, which arose in the late Bronze Age, is known for its use in the Vedas. The<em> Ramayana</em> and <em>Mahabharata</em> were written in, for the point, what ancient sacred language of the Indian subcontinent?", "answer": "<b><u>Sanskrit</u></b> (accept Vedic <b><u>Sanskrit</u></b>)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {}, {"question": "Using the<em> numeri</em> auxiliary system, this general introduced Eastern mounted archers and cataphracts into the Legion. This proponent of \"Strength through Peace\" rebuilt the Pantheon following its partial destruction during a 114 fire. This man accepted Antoninus Pius as his successor on the condition that he appoint Marcus Aurelius and Lucius Verus as his heirs. A wall crossing Roman Britain was built by, for the point, which of the \"Five Good Emperors\"?", "answer": "<b><u>Hadrian</u></b> (accept Caesar Trajanus <b><u>Hadrian</u></b>us; do not accept \"Trajan\" alone)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man openly condemned a past administration's 1961 crackdown on Algerian citizens under police chief Maurice Papon [[pah-POHN]]. This man's foreign minister Jean-Yves Le Drian [[zhon-EEV luh dree-AHN]] called the signing of the AUKUS pact a \"stab in the back.\" This successor of Francoise Hollande [[oh-LAHND]] defeated Marine Le Pen [[luh-PAHN]] in a 2017 electoral run-off. The Yellow-Vest protests occurred during the administration of, for the point, which French president?", "answer": "Emmanuel <b><u>Macron</u></b> (or Emmanuel Jean-Michel Fr\u00e9d\u00e9ric <b><u>Macron</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man's forces met disaster against Marinid sultan Salah ibn Salah at the 1437 Battle of Tangiers, after which this man's brother, Ferdinand, was given as a hostage. This royal supposedly based his efforts out of a villa on the Sagres [[SAH-greesh]] peninsula, from which he funded several caravel voyages to the Bay of Arguin [[ahr-GEEN]], Madeira [[muh-DEEH-ruh]], and the Azores [[uh-ZORZ]]. For the point, name this fifteenth-century Portuguese prince, often credited with jumpstarting the Age of Exploration.", "answer": "Prince <b><u>Henry the Navigator</u></b> (or Infante Dom <b><u>Henrique, o Navegador</u></b>; or <b><u>Infante</u> <u>Dom Henrique</u></b> [note: in Portuguese, \"the Navigator\" title is not typically attached to Henry's name])", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<em>Protostrator</em> Manuel Kamytzes [[kam-ITE-zeez]] harassed soldiers en route to this war while they were unable to cross from Thrace into Anatolia. During this war, the weight of his horse's armor led to the drowning of Emperor Frederick Barbarossa while crossing the Saleph [[SAH-leff]] River. Following this war's Battle of Jaffa [[JAH-fah]], Richard the Lionheart and Saladin agreed to peaceful terms. For the point, name this 12th century \"Crusade\" prompted by the Saracen [[SAY-ruh-sen]] capture of Jerusalem.", "answer": "<b><u>Third</u></b> Crusade (accept the <b><u>King's</u></b> Crusade)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "It's not Afghanistan, but<em> mujahideen</em> [[moo-jah-hih-DEEN]] guerillas in this nation's Mayu Peninsula agitated for the right to be annexed by a western neighbor. Mao's support of the \"Red Flags\" in this nation led to its president, Ne Win, cutting off relations with China. This nation's Tatmadaw [[TAT-mad-aw]] armed forces overthrew the government of Aung San Suu Kyi [[CHEE]] in 2021. The repression of the Rohingya [[row-HIN-gah]] people occurred in, for the point, what nation also known as Burma?", "answer": "<b><u>Myanmar</u></b> (accept Republic of the Union of <b><u>Myanmar</u></b>; or Pyidaunzu Thanm\u0103da <b><u>My</u><u>\u0103</u><u>ma</u></b> Nainngandaw; accept <b><u>Burma</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Plumber Max H\u00f6del [[HUH-del]] attempted to kill a monarch with this name after he was expelled from the Social Democratic Party. The second ruler of this name from the House of Hohenzollern became a figurehead in the final years of his reign, conceding power to Erich Ludendorff and Paul von Hindenburg. That monarch of this name dismissed longtime chancellor Otto von Bismarck two years into his reign. The Kaiser at the beginning of World War One had, for the point, what regnal given name?", "answer": "Kaiser <b><u>Wilhelm</u></b> (accept <b><u>Wilhelm</u></b> I or <b><u>Wilhelm</u></b> II; accept <b><u>William</u></b> in place of <b><u>Wilhelm</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "A princess and a warrior from this culture were supposedly transfigured into the stratovolcanoes Popocatepl [[poh-poh-kah-TEH-pill]] and Iztaccihuatl [[ees-stah-keh-HWAH-til]]. Known as the \"hand-made mountain,\" the abandoned Great Pyramid of Cholula was a pilgrimage site for these people. Within the \"Sacred Precinct\" of these people was the Templo Mayor complex, which was simultaneously dedicated to Huitzilopochtli [[hweet-zee-loh-POACH-tlee]] and Tlaloc. For the point, name this Mesoamerican people who worshiped Quetzalcoatl [[KWEH-tsuhl-KWAH-tul]] and built Tenochtitlan [[teh-nohtch-TEET-lahn]].", "answer": "<b><u>Aztec</u></b> (accept <b><u>Mexica</u></b>; or <b><u>Nahua</u></b>tl)", "metadata": "Mythology - Mythology"}, {"question": "This monarch's sister Berenice [[beh-reh-NEE-kay]] IV died at the hands of her father after he paid Aulus Gabinius [[OW-looss gah-BIH-nee-ooss]] to reclaim his throne. While visiting a Triumvir in Cilicia, this ruler dressed as a nude Aphrodite on a golden barge sailing down the Cydnus [[SID-nooss]] river. This mother of Caesarion supposedly killed herself with asps before being captured by Octavian. For the point, name this last Ptolemaic ruler, a queen of Egypt and paramour of Mark Antony.", "answer": "<b><u>Cleopatra</u></b> VII Philopator", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "The first Japanese people to visit this kingdom was the crew of the<em> Inawaka-maru</em>, who broke isolationist policy. Sanford Dole's provisional government succeeded this kingdom, nearly going to war with the U.S. during Black Week after planters refused to reinstate Queen Lili\u02bbuokalani [[leh-LEE-oh-kah-LAH-nee]]. Kamehameha [[kah-MEH-hah-MEH-hah]] the Great's conquests of islands including Moloka\u02bbi and Oahu formed, for the point, what Polynesian kingdom that was annexed into the United States?", "answer": "Kingdom of <b><u>Hawaii</u></b> (or <b><u>Hawaii</u></b>an Kingdom; accept Aupuni M\u014d\u02bb\u012b o <b><u>Hawai</u><u>\u02bb</u><u>i</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the carrier<em> Oriskany</em> nearly sank after a soldier accidentally lit a flare and threw it in a locker, causing a fire that killed 44 sailors. During this conflict, naval trawlers attempted to drop supplies to sites along the B\u1ed3\u0110\u1ec1[[BOH-DEH]] River including Nha Trang to get past U.S. personnel. Operation Custom Tailor was a dedicated naval bombardment of Haiphong Harbor during this war. For the point, name this 1955-1975 Southeast Asian conflict?", "answer": "<b><u>Vietnam</u></b> War (or Chi\u1ebfn tranh <b><u>Vi</u><u>\u1ec7</u><u>t Nam</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In this nation, the housewife Mary Jackson used Belvidere Baptist Church to organize a bread riot in its capital city. John Pool led the Red Strings society, aiming to peacefully end a war fought by this breakaway state and return to its mother nation. This state believed \"King Cotton\" would pull the UK into the war on their side. The surrender at Appomattox Courthouse nominally ended, for the point, what state, which fought the Union in the U.S. Civil War?", "answer": "The <b><u>Confederacy</u></b> (accept the <b><u>Confederate States</u></b> of America; accept <b><u>CSA</u></b>; prompt on \"South\"; do not accept the \"USA\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this state, editor John Peter Zenger successfully won a libel case brought on by this state's sitting colonial governor. Later converted into a silverware company, the utopian \"Oneida [[oh-NYE-duh]] Community\" in this state attempted to create Jesus's Millennial Kingdom on earth. This state's largest city was the headquarters for the British during the American Revolution following the Battle of Long Island. The Albany Congress occurred in, for the point, what Mid-Atlantic state?", "answer": "<b><u>New York</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A Pulitzer Prize-winning story describing an eight year-old heroin addict in this city, \"Jimmy's World,\" was promoted by Mayor Marion Barry even after he discovered it was fabricated. Detailed logs about an event in this city from \"Deep Throat\" are recorded in<em> All</em> <em>the President's Men</em> by Carl Bernstein and Bob Woodward, who broke the Watergate scandal. <em>The Pentagon Papers</em> were published by, for the point, what city's paper, the<em> Post</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Washington</u></b> <b><u>D.C.</u></b> (accept either underlined portion; accept the <b><u>District of</u> <u>Columbia</u></b>, accept <em><b><u>Washington</u></b> Post</em>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "While extracting this commodity, peasants developed the<em> Yangge</em> [[YAHNG-GUH]] style of folk song during the Song Dynasty. A Taoist state ruled by the \"Celestial Masters\" during the Three Kingdoms period required that adherents donate \"Five Pecks\" of this commodity. In legend, Guan Yin gave this food to the Chinese people to end their starvation. Paddies are used to grow, for the point, what chief grain of East Asia?", "answer": "<b><u>Rice</u></b> (accept <b><u>Baifan</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Under the guise of it being a wartime morale booster, FDR sent the \"Green Light Letter\" to Commissioner Kennesaw Landis urging him to keep this sport going. Branch Rickey, an owner in this sport, scouted talent among the<em> nisei</em> inmates in internment camps. \"The Luckiest Man on the Face of the Earth\" speech was given by a retiring player in this sport, Lou Gehrig. The nickname \"America's Pastime\" was given to, for the point, what sport played by Jackie Robinson?", "answer": "<b><u>Baseball</u></b> (accept Major League <b><u>Baseball</u></b>; or <b><u>MLB</u></b>)", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "This nation's Almirante Brown Antarctica base was burned down by a scientist after he was ordered to stay the winter. This country's National Reorganization Process led to a period of state terrorism known as \"La Guerra Sucia\" [[soo-SEE-ah]], or the Dirty War. The \"Shirtless Ones\" dominated post-war politics of this nation under the leadership of Juan Per\u00f3n. Per\u00f3n ruled from Buenos Aires in, for the point, what South American nation?", "answer": "<b><u>Argentina</u></b> (accept <b><u>Argentine</u></b> Republic; or Rep\u00fablica <b><u>Argentina</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "During the August Movement, this figure gave the \"Do or Die\" speech, advocating for an end to violent resistance during the Second World War. American vice-consul Herbert Reiner captured this man's assassin following an attack at the Birla House. The British Raj's taxes on a certain good led to this man organizing the Salt March to Dandi. The term <em>Mahatma</em> was bestowed upon, for the point, which Indian freedom fighter?", "answer": "Mohandas <b><u>Gandhi</u></b> (accept Mahatma <b><u>Gandhi</u></b>; or Mohandas Karamchand <b><u>Gandhi</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "That work of this type is \"A Mighty Fortress is Our God.\" The biblical Book of Psalms is a collection of these songs supposedly written by King David. For the point, name these religious songs written in adoration of God.", "answer": "<b><u>Hymn</u></b>s (prompt on descriptive answers)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "It's not Bangkok, but the Dusit Thani [[DOO-sit TAH-nee]] building in this city is meant to represent hands performing a traditional Thai greeting. This city\u2019s man-made archipelago known as \u201cThe World\u201d remains largely undeveloped due to the 2008 financial crisis. In 2009, this city became home to the largest building in the world, the Burj Khalifa. For the point, identify this city, the namesake of one of the seven emirates that make up the UAE.", "answer": "<b><u>Dubai</u></b> (or <b><u>Dubayy</u></b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "During this journey, a bluff along the Missouri River was named for officer Charles Floyd, who died of a ruptured appendix. This expedition constructed Fort Clatsop on the Columbia river shortly before reaching the Pacific Ocean. The hiring of trapper Toussaint Charbonneau [[shar-bah-NOH]] led to this group recruiting the Shoshone [[shoh-SHOH-neh]] translator Sacagawea [[sah-kah-juh-WEH-ah]]. The Corps of Discovery undertook, for the point, what \"Expedition\" to explore the Louisiana territory?", "answer": "<b><u>Lewis</u></b> and <b><u>Clark</u></b> Expedition (accept the <b><u>Corps of Discovery</u></b> Expedition before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "An early musical component added to this genre by Afro-Creole musician \"Jelly Roll\" Morton was known as the \"Spanish Tinge.\" Ornette Coleman was an early pioneer of this genre's \"Free\" form, releasing<em> The Shape of [this genre] to Come</em> in the late 1950s. The interwar years in the United States are sometimes known as \"The Age of\" this musical style. For the point, name this improvisational genre of music whose practitioners include Miles Davis and Duke Ellington.", "answer": "<b><u>Jazz</u></b> (accept Free <b><u>Jazz</u></b>; accept<em> The Shape of</em> <em><b><u>Jazz</u></b> to Come</em>; accept The Age of <b><u>Jazz</u></b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Plasma torch gasification may be applied to this general type of material to prevent methane pollution and has been added to the U.S. Navy's<em> Gerald R. Ford</em> class aircraft carriers. The company Bigbelly produces a solar-powered machine that compacts this material. Accumulation of this material in oceanic gyres [[JIRES]] creates namesake patches, including one named the \"Great Pacific.\" For the point, name this material stored in landfills.", "answer": "<b><u>Garbage</u></b> (or <b><u>trash</u></b>, or <b><u>waste</u></b>, or <b><u>refuse</u></b>, or <b><u>rubbish</u></b>, accept word forms and other equivalent answers: accept Great Pacific <b><u>Garbage</u></b> Patch; prompt on \"pollution\")", "metadata": "Science - Other Science - Earth Science"}, {"question": "This man's illegitimate son, William, served as the final colonial governor of New Jersey. This man organized the militia which halted the marauding Paxton Boys's march on Philadelphia. This diplomat, who secured French intervention in the American Revolution, also invented conventional bifocals. For the point, name this American Renaissance man and Founding Father who served as the United States's first Postmaster General.", "answer": "Benjamin <b><u>Franklin</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "One of these structures named for Emperor Domitian inspired the Statius [[STAY-shee-us]] poem<em> The Elements of Balance</em>. The<em> Quattuorviri</em> [[KWAH-twohr-VEE-ree]] was a quartet of magistrates appointed by the Republic who oversaw the maintenance of these structures. The<em> cursus publicus</em> was a courier system under Augustus which used these constructs to quickly deliver mail. Rome and Brundisium were connected by, for the point, what type of construct known as the<em> Via Appia</em>?", "answer": "<b><u>Road</u></b>s (accept more specific answers like Roman <b><u>Roads</u></b>; accept synonyms like <b><u>Causeway</u></b>s; accept <b><u>Via</u></b> Appia before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This politician's namesake \"Doctrine\" allowed for Middle Eastern nations to directly request American military and financial aid. This president's Farewell Address warned of the growing Military-Industrial Complex and large-scale deficit spending. This man's time in occupied Germany and visit to the Autobahn inspired his promotion of the Interstate Highway System. For the point, name this general-turned-president in the 1950s, nicknamed \"Ike.\"", "answer": "Dwight D(avid) \"Ike\" <b><u>Eisenhower</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In order to protect this monarch and his family, Leopold II and Frederick William II threatened war in the Declaration of Pillnitz. The Marquis de Lafayette put down a riot against this monarch, resulting in the Champ de Mars [[SHAHMP duh MAHR]] Massacre. The National Convention convicted this king of high treason and executed him by guillotine in Revolution Square. The husband of Marie Antoinette was, for the point, which Bourbon king, deposed by the French Revolution?", "answer": "<b><u>Louis XVI</u></b> [[\"the sixteenth\"]] (prompt on \"Louis Capet\" or \"Citizen Capet\")", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}